{"tossups": [{"question": "Large statues of overweight men on the shoulders of naked servants have been found at the archaeological site of Barriles in this country. Upon arriving in New York City after leaving this modern country, the passengers aboard the Unicorn learned that two ships had already left to resupply them, which convinced them to return to this country. A conquistador in this modern country set his dogs on 40 native men in this country for engaging in homosexual acts. This country\u2019s equivalents to the quilombos were the cimarrones who joined with (*) Francis Drake to fight the Spanish and interrupt their transport of silver. The 1707 Act of Union was prompted by the failure of a Scottish colony in this country. For 10 points, name this Central American country once ruled by Manuel Noriega and crossed by Vasco Nu\u00f1ez de Balboa.", "answer": "Republic of Panama", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Republic of <b><u>Panama</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Republic of Panama", "Panama"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man wrote his autobiography at the request of Dr. Heinrich Brode who translated it into German and it is the first known example of that type of literature in his native language. A man who supposedly could not be killed by guns unless his amulets were removed and he was shot in the ear, Gongo Lutete, defected from the forces of this man during a conflict led by his son Sefu. This man declared himself Sultan of Utetera and was supported by the Nyamwezi people after establishing a trading base at Kasongo. This man was promised control of Boyoma Falls for his assistance in the (*) Emin Pasha Relief Expedition. This man is best known by a name derived from the sound of his guns. For 10 points, identify this 19th century Zanzibari slave and ivory trader.", "answer": "Tippu Tip (accept Hamed bin Muhammed al-Murjebi)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Tippu Tip</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Tippu Tip", "Tippu Tip"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Hamed bin Muhammed al-Murjebi"}, {"question": "A ruler who conquered this city was so impressed by its architecture that he issued a 1458 firman to ensure its protection. This city was the center of a political unit called a veguer\u00eda for most of the 14th century during which time it was known as Cetines. This city suffered a 582 CE sack at the hands of the Slavs and was later conquered by Nerio I Acciajuoli of Florence. This city\u2019s namesake duchy was subject to the Assizes of Romania. During the Morean War, this city\u2019s garrison was deported to (*) Smyrna after it was taken by Francesco Morosini. One building in this city was converted into a mosque by the Ottomans and was later destroyed during a Venetian siege when it was used as a gunpowder store. For 10 points, this is what city, which had earlier been the home of Pericles and Socrates?", "answer": "Athens (or Athenai)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Athens</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Athens", "Athens"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "or Athenai"}, {"question": "This treaty created the \u201cStep Boundary\u201d due in part to the belief that the source of a certain river lay near the 42nd parallel. One impetus for this agreement was the raids conducted from the \u201cNegro Fort\u201d, now Fort Gadsden. The 1828 Treaty of Limits extended the terms of this agreement. The unresolved controversy left by the Nootka Convention also prompted this negotiation. This treaty resolved the controversy over the (*) Neutral Ground between the Calcasieu and Sabine Rivers. One signatory of this agreement gave up claims to land north of 42\u00b0 to focus on rebellious provinces farther south. For 10 points, name this 1819 treaty between the US and Spain that gave the US control of Florida and set the boundary between the Missouri Territory and New Spain.", "answer": "Adams-On\u00eds Treaty (accept Transcontinental Treaty, Florida Treaty, or Florida Purchase Treaty)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Adams-On\u00eds</u></b> Treaty", "acceptable": ["Adams-On\u00eds Treaty", "Adams-On\u00eds"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Transcontinental Treaty, Florida Treaty, or Florida Purchase Treaty"}, {"question": "Elizabeth Barrett Browning\u2019s first published poem, published at the age of 6, was written on this practice. The Easton Massacre was prompted by a reaction against this practice. A secondary effect of the 1597 Vagabonds Act was to promote this practice. This practice was apocryphally carried out by dropping coins into people\u2019s drinks; those affected were claimed to have \u201cagreed\u201d to this practice by finding the coin. This process dispreferred (*) \u201clandsmen\u201d. The application of this practice against Americans was a source of tension leading to the War of 1812 and was the cause of the HMS Leopard affair. For 10 points, identify this practice of forcefully recruiting men into European navies, most commonly associated with the British.", "answer": "British impressment (prompt on conscription or similar answers)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "British <b><u>impressment</u></b>", "acceptable": ["British impressment", "impressment"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on conscription or similar answers"}, {"question": "The first well-documented exploratory expedition on this island was carried out by the Akmana Gold Prospecting Company, which encountered a people they called \u201cwig-men\u201d. The city of Fakfak was once a significant port on this island in the region the Nagarakretagama calls Wanin. The Kuk swamp on this island contains some of the earliest evidence for the cultivation of taro and bananas. A company named after this island was founded by Adolph von Hansemann to forward the (*) German colonization of the northeast of this island, which was contemporaneous with Dutch occupation of the western half and British possession of the SE and largest city, Port Moresby. For 10 points, identify this island, the world\u2019s second largest, now split between Indonesia in the west and its eponymous country in the east.", "answer": "New Guinea (accept Irian; do not accept or prompt on Papua New Guinea or Irian Jaya as those terms only refer to parts of the island)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>New Guinea</u></b>", "acceptable": ["New Guinea", "New Guinea"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept Irian; do not accept or prompt on Papua New Guinea or Irian Jaya as those terms only refer to parts of the island"}, {"question": "A notable part of this system is the Q\u2019iswa Chaka, which is rebuilt every June out of ichhu grass. One type of building along this system shared a name with the Pleiades constellation and such buildings were highly concentrated in the Mantaro Valley. The most famous section of this infrastructure system passes through an area whose name translates to \u201cdead woman\u201d. The most frequent users of this infrastructure system blew on horns called (*) pututus to announce their coming. This infrastructure system was lined with inns called tambos and warehouses called qullqas. This infrastructure system traversed by the chaski linked the four provinces of the Tawantinsuyu. For 10 points, identify this infrastructure system that interconnected the Andes created by a government based out of Cuzco.", "answer": "Incan road system (accept equivalents)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Incan road system</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Incan road system", "Incan road system"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents"}, {"question": "This man wrote a letter to Philip II of Spain in which he calls himself \u201crebel until death against you for your ingratitude\u201d and claims that kings are worse than Lucifer. After being sentenced to a public flogging for cruelty towards indigenous people, this man hunted the judge who sentenced him for three years before finding and killing him in Cuzco. After conquering Isla Margarita, this leader landed on the mainland in an attempt to take Panama. This man usurped and killed his commander (*) Pedro de Urs\u00faa on an expedition through the Amazon Rainforest from Peru. For 10 points, name this conquistador who gave himself the epithet \u201cWrath of God\u201d, the subject of a 1972 Werner Herzog film starring Klaus Kinski.", "answer": "Lope de Aguirre, Wrath of God, Prince of Freedom, King of Tierra Firme (prompt on \u201cWrath of God\u201d until mentioned)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Lope de Aguirre, Wrath of God, Prince of Freedom, King of Tierra Firme</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Lope de Aguirre, Wrath of God, Prince of Freedom, King of Tierra Firme", "Lope de Aguirre, Wrath of God, Prince of Freedom, King of Tierra Firme"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "prompt on \u201cWrath of God\u201d until mentioned"}, {"question": "The distribution of \u201clong-nosed god maskettes\u201d is among the evidence supporting the theory that this site was the center of a missionizing religion. A burial at this site is believed to contain an impersonator of the culture hero Red Horn, or \u201cHe Who Wears Human Heads as Earrings\u201d. This site contains the earliest known evidence for the consumption of Black Drink. A game in which players try to throw spears at the spot where a rolling stone stops originated at this site. The first place where (*) chunkey was played, the most famous feature of this site was named for the French Trappists who briefly lived on it in the early 19th century. Home to Monk\u2019s Mound, for 10 points, name this center of the Mississippian culture and the only Pre-Columbian city north of Mexico.", "answer": "Cahokia", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Cahokia</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Cahokia", "Cahokia"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One of these events in Mapuche myth is caused by a battle between the serpents Kaykayfilu and Trengtrengfilu. In Aztec myth, the children of Coxcox (\u201ckoash-koash\u201d) and Xochiquetzal (\u201cshow-chee-KAY-tsal\u201d) are taught how to speak by a dove after one of these events. The Lebor Gab\u00e1la \u00c9renn attributes the settlement of Ireland to a group of people led by Cessair fleeing one of these events. Before making a sacrifice to the moon, Nu\u2019u is (*) placed on top of Mauna Kea by one of these events. The reigns of rulers is reduced from thousands to hundreds of years in the Sumerian King List after one of these events. One of these events occurs after V\u00e4in\u00e4m\u00f6inen wounds his knee and is unable to staunch the blood himself. Vi\u1e63\u1e47u incarnates as the fish Matsya to save Manu from, for 10 points, what type of mythological event, another one of which is survived by Noah?", "answer": "floods", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>floods</u></b>", "acceptable": ["floods", "floods"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "After being a primary ringleader in an unemployment protest in Trafalgar Square, this woman offered herself up to be arrested, but the police refused. As a member of the Fabian Society, she became close with George Bernard Shaw, even inviting him to live with her. With Charles Bradlaugh, this woman was arrested for publishing a book on birth control by Charles Knowlton. After writing a review for the Pall Mall Gazette on the book The Secret Garden, this woman (*) converted to her most famous belief. This woman may be most famous for grooming Jiddu Krishnamurti as the \u201cWorld Teacher\u201d, a title he would later renounce. For 10 points, name this 19th century political activist and successor to Helena Blavatsky, the second president of the Theosophical Society.", "answer": "Annie Besant", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Annie Besant</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Annie Besant", "Annie Besant"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The first European town in this modern state was the Dutch town of Zwaanendael. One settlement in this state had a wharf built on a formation called the \u201cRocks\u201d and had defenses built by Peter Ridder. That settlement was founded by a man who later died in a hurricane on his return to Europe. The courthouse of this state\u2019s town of New Castle was used as the center of the Twelve-Mile Circle which settled a boundary dispute with its northern neighbor. (*) James, Duke of York\u2019s possession this modern state was contested by Cecil Calvert. Sir Robert Carr brought this state under British control after taking it from the Dutch. Home of Fort Christina, for 10 points, this is which state with its current capital at Dover?", "answer": "Delaware", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Delaware</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Delaware", "Delaware"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In 2014, director Pamela Yates discovered that she had misrepresented who carried out a massacre in a film centering on this person\u2019s life and the related film Granito: How to Nail a Dictator. In 1999, this person filed charges in Spain against several of their countrymen for ordering the brutal 1980 suppression of a peaceful occupation of the Spanish embassy by peasants in her country. David Stoll controversially disputed this person\u2019s claim to have witnessed the burning of her (*) brother Petrocinio as recounted in a biography. This member of the Winaq party and subject of the documentary When the Mountains Tremble brought the first criminal charges against Efra\u00edn R\u00edos Montt. This K\u2019iche woman received 3.09% of the vote as the first presidential candidate for the party Encuentro por Guatemala. For 10 points, who is this woman, an activist for indigenous rights in Guatemala?", "answer": "Rigoberta Mench\u00fa Tum", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "Rigoberta Mench\u00fa <b><u>Tum</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Rigoberta Mench\u00fa Tum", "Tum"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "In one meeting, a scholar from this region reinterprets the meaning of a cave painting which depicts one light surrounded by three smaller ones. A young man with a sword kills most of the wildlife in this region in a myth before being admonished by a creature that can disappear into its own alternate dimension. After saving its life, Damos was given a jewel formed from five elemental plates by the creator of this region. Three guardian spirits of this region are based on the Imperial Regalia of Japan and dwell in lakes (*) Acuity, Verity, and Valor. A story from this region explains that the mutual assistance and friendship between Pok\u00e9mon and humans is why Pok\u00e9mon appear in tall grass. Many of this region\u2019s myths are collected in the library of Canalave City and are studied by its Pok\u00e9mon League Champion Cynthia. For 10 points, what is this region, the setting of the fourth generation Pok\u00e9mon games?", "answer": "Sinnoh", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Sinnoh</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Sinnoh", "Sinnoh"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "An event of this type was carried out after the death of Enrique de Villena in 1434 due to the belief that he was a necromancer. One of these actions was done to appease the Dominican Order after Nachmanides won the Disputation of Barcelona. The kingdom of Castile followed the Roman rite instead of the Mozarabic rite because of the outcome of a trial by ordeal carried out as one of these events. Apologists for an instigator of one of these events claim that the damage done by it was mitigated by the work (*) Relaci\u00f3n de las Cosas de Yucat\u00e1n. That action was undertaken by Diego de Landa, from which the Paris, Madrid, and Dresden Codices are the most famous survivors. For 10 points, identify these events that see collections of bound paper raised to or above a temperature of around 451o F.", "answer": "book burnings (accept logical equivalents; prompt on answers that suggest the books are being destroyed but doesn\u2019t specify burning)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>book burnings</u></b>", "acceptable": ["book burnings", "book burnings"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept logical equivalents; prompt on answers that suggest the books are being destroyed but doesn\u2019t specify burning"}, {"question": "Descriptive answer acceptable Over 600 people died when the Violet and the Duke William sank in a storm while carrying out this process. This process officially began soon after the Battle of Fort Beaus\u00e9jour. The Foreign Protestants, settlers from Germany, were brought in to counter the demographic changes brought about by this process. This process could be reversed from 1764 on pending an oath of unconditional allegiance from affected individuals. Hostilities surrounding this action featured a Burying of the Hatchet ceremony between the British and the (*) Mi\u2019kmaq who had allied with the affected people. This event resulted in a large number of people moving to Louisiana after a brief stay in Europe. For 10 points, identify this event that kicked the French out of Nova Scotia.", "answer": "expulsion of the Acadians (accept equivalents; prompt on Ile Saint Jean Campaign, French and Indian War/equivalents, or anything saying that the British are fighting the French in Nova Scotia or Canada)", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>expulsion of the Acadians</u></b>", "acceptable": ["expulsion of the Acadians", "expulsion of the Acadians"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": "accept equivalents; prompt on Ile Saint Jean Campaign, French and Indian War/equivalents, or anything saying that the British are fighting the French in Nova Scotia or Canada"}, {"question": "This leader took Torna Fort at the age of 16, perhaps by bribing its commander Inayat Khan. A commander under this man apocryphally scaled the walls of Sinhagad with the help of monitor lizards. One of this man\u2019s enemies referred to him as \u201cMountain Rat\u201d after his victory at the Battle of Kolhapur. That same enemy sent a 150,000 man army against this leader, which this ruler defeated by infiltrating Pune as part of a wedding party and nearly capturing its general Shaista Khan. During a parley, this man mortally wounded (*) Afzal Khan with a weapon called a \u201ctiger claw\u201d. After his early fighting with the Adil Shahi Dynasty of Bijapur, this man established a powerful empire in the Deccan, which frequently clashed the Mughals under Aurangzeb. For 10 points, name this founder of the Maratha Empire.", "answer": "Chhatrapati Shivaji Bhonsle", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Chhatrapati Shivaji Bhonsle</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Chhatrapati Shivaji Bhonsle", "Chhatrapati Shivaji Bhonsle"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "The graduates of one school for these people supposedly used a technique called \u201creverse egg flow\u201d that gave men visions of their death while having sex. The most famous of these people has been inaccurately claimed to have been killed with burning oil in a naval battle in the Inland Sea. The construction of \u201cnightingale floors\u201d that \u201cchirp\u201d when stepped on was a means of countering these people. After copying an enemy lantern design, a group of these people infiltrated and burned (*) Sawayama Castle. The K\u014dga and Iga clans were the most famous and prolific in producing these people, represented by Mochizuki Chiyome and Hattori Hanz\u014d, respectively. For 10 points, name these covert operatives of feudal Japan, often depicted in the West as super soldiers in black or teenage mutant turtles.", "answer": "ninjas or shinobi", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>ninjas or shinobi</u></b>", "acceptable": ["ninjas or shinobi", "ninjas or shinobi"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "This man\u2019s daughter married Naravas, a general who had previously defected to join this man and helped him win the Battle of Bagradas River. This general allied with the Tartessians to secure a source of silver, minting coins from the nearby city of Gadir, and may have died while crossing the Jucar River while campaigning against the Oretani. This leader fought Numerius Fabius Buteo shortly after killing or exiling a group of rebellious (*) mercenaries. This general was scapegoated by his government, which claimed he caused the Truceless War by promising his troops too much payment. Famously said to have made his oldest son swear never to be a \u201cFriend of Rome\u201d, this is, for 10 points, what Carthaginian general of the First Punic War and father of Hannibal?", "answer": "Hamilcar Barca", "category": "History", "answer_formatted": "<b><u>Hamilcar Barca</u></b>", "acceptable": ["Hamilcar Barca", "Hamilcar Barca"], "promptable": [], "rejectable": [], "metadata": ""}, {"question": "One account claims that this city was once saved from attack by a divinely sent flock of birds carrying brimstone that bombarded the invading army. During a siege, a structure in this city was apocryphally damaged when the wooden structure covered with mattresses surrounding it caught on fire and fell on it. The Turkish government compared the demolition of the Ottoman-era Ajyad Fort in this city to the destruction of the Buddhas of Bamiyan. A war elephant named Mahmud, part of an invading (*) Ethiopian army, supposedly refused to enter this city, leading the year of the birth of the most important resident of this city to be called the Year of the Elephant. The Black Stone was taken by the Qarmatians in their 930 sack of this city. This city was the capital of the short-lived Kingdom of Hejaz before being conquered by the forces of the newly forming Saudi state. For 10 points, name this holiest city in Islam.", "category": "History"}], "bonuses": []}